MICHEL KARAM

UI / UX / VISUAL & INTERACTION DESIGNER

(514) 833 4110

mkaram@videotron.ca
Portfolio: michelkaram.net

Linkedin: http://ca.linkedin.com/in/michelkaram

1575 Louis-Carrier #201 Montreal, Qc, H4N 2Z7 Canada

Senior UI / UX and Interaction Designer with a BAC in graphic design obtained in 1999 from the UQAM.

Strong experience in usability and user interface design (for B2B and B2C solutions), covering desktop software, Web Apps, Mobile (iOS / Android and Windows) as well as large-scale interactive projects.

Worked in Canada and the USA in graphic, Web and interaction design. Continously adapting to the latest practices in UI / UX design. Since 2011, worked on many design projects for mobile apps along with some experiments and interventions in augmented and mixed reality projects.

Solid skills and experience in working with development teams as well as discussing projects and features with clients and users in order to translate their strategic objectives into visual or interactive solutions.

Able to work alone or in a team, can make quick decisions and manage tasks in their various aspects.

Easily adapts to any work environment; Experience since 2011 in Agile / SCRUM practices.

UX certification from ETS in 2015.

Fluent in French and English (spoken and written).

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Terranova Security	Laval, Qc	UI / UX Design	2018 – Présent
Spiria	Montreal, Qc	UI / UX / Mobile / Web Design	2011 – 2018
Deloitte	Montreal, Qc	Graphic & Interaction Desgin	2011
20-20 Technologies	Laval, Qc	Web / Web App Design / Art Direction	2003 – 2011
Consultant / Freelancer	Montreal, Qc	Graphic & Web Design / Coordination	2002 – 2003
Stylus	Montreal, Qc	Web Design	2001 – 2002
marchFIRST	Dallas, Tx, USA	Graphic & Web Design	2000 – 2001
UQAM	Montreal, Qc	Web Design	1998 – 1999
Dorval Community Center	Dorval, Qc	Graphic Design / Ilustration	1995 – 1997
Projet Florence (Consultant)	Laval, Qc	Art Direction / Web Design	2011
Lebor Simulations (Consultant)	Montreal, Qc	Art Direction / Coordination	1998 – 2020

MAIN ROLES AND ACHIEVEMENTS

In the companies and agencies above.

UI / UX Design for software and complex Web or mobile applications:

For: Terranova Security / Spiria / 20-20 Technologies.

- Design and improvement of user interfaces and usability for an e-learning / content management platform (Terranova Security).
- Responsible for the usability and user interfaces of a large scale application for managing show business events to increase the efficiency of the process.
- Helped optimize and modernize the management of the staff, products and stores with professional Web and mobile applications for companies such as: *Acosta, Bombardier, iBwave et Giro.*
- Participated in brainstorming sessions with the projects' teams to discuss and resolve design challenges in applications with complex business rules.
- Offered optimal solutions through prototypes (wireframes) for the applications' usability and user interfaces.
- Created preliminary and detailed mockups for the different UIs as well as interactive prototypes for client presentations
- Created visual components as needed, such as icons or illustrations for application interfaces.
- Designed the visual brand elements for several of these applications (Logos, color palettes and design guides).
- Worked with Front-End developers to ensure the applications meet the mockups visual standards and specifications.
- Worked with development teams using the Agile / SCRUM process.

Design of Web user interfaces:

For: Spiria / 20-20 Technologies / Projet Florence / Lebor Simulations / Stylus / marchFirst / other projects as a freelancer or consultant.

- Modernized the Websites of companies and associations by designing UIs according to current visual and technological practices such as adaptability and accessibility: Cran, Centura, DESTL, Lebor Simulations.
- Created an original and modern Website UX for wine lovers: Projet Florence.
- Designed Website UIs for used vehicle portals and for Canadian car dealership associations such as: CCAQ, Occasion en Or, AMVOQ et CarrXpert.
- Improved the online visual brand of several associations and companies by designing Website interfaces for clients such as: *Pearl Levy sculptures, Braque, Peer Gynt Yachts, Pâtisserie Ngan Ha.*
- Contributed to improving the online experience and brands for clients like: BCE / Emergis, Foule Jeu, Canadian Pacific Railways, Canadian Ski Marathon.
- Contributed to the growth of online sales by designing Websites and Web Ads for company portals: *JCPenney, AT&T, Pier 1 Imports et American Airlines*.

Helped promote the UQAM Sports Center and increase student subscriptions by creating the new sports center Website.

Interaction / Multimedia design:

For: Spiria / 20-20 Technologie / Projet Florence / Lebor Simulations / Stylus / marchFirst / UQAM

- Designed an interactive gamified experience for a show to promote digital Barcode technology.
- Created animated conceptual banners for the company's newspaper (design, script and animation).
- Helped introduce new corporate strategies by designing Web and interactive projects for the employees.
- Designed user frirendly and modern Uls for professional interior design software.
- Helped increase online visits and sales by creating kitchen and bathroom planners Uls for companies such as: Home
 Depot, Lowe's et B&Q.
- Helped promoting the corporate strategy (20-20 End-to-End) by creating the script and storyboard of a corporate promotional video.
- Helped managers communicate their strategic visions by designing interactive and modern presentations (Powerpoint).

Graphic design:

For: Spiria / 20-20 Technologies / Lebor Simulations / Stylus / marchFirst / Ville de Dorval / autres projets à titre de pigiste ou consultant.

- Created corporate promotional material for companies (print or web).
- Updated and improved the corporate visual brand and that of products and services by creating: Brochures, flyers, packaging, logos, advertisements, presentations, banners and event posters as well as promotional emails and internal document layouts.
- Create corporate event branding images and apply them to sweaters or promotional items.
- Participated in promoting corporate departments by creating corporate advertising posters.
- Contributed to increase the number of participants in the events of the City of Dorval by creating posters for its Community Center.
- Helped to organize the internal spaces of the company by collaborating on decoration projects (design of visual / decorative elements).

Art Direction / Coordination of graphic or interactive projects:

Pour : Spiria / Projet Florence / Lebor Simulations / other projects as a freelancer or consultant.

- Created, improved and modernized the corporate image and that of products and services by designing:
 - The visual brand and its components (Logos, promotions etc.)
 - Establishing precise standards and graphics for product branding and services.
 - Development of attractive graphic, Web or interactive concepts.
 - Creating precise scripts and story-boards for promotional videos.
- Ensured the quality of the production and the application of the visual brand by coaching graphic designers or front-end developers.
- Ensured the application of the visual brand as well as the graphic standards by monitoring and coordinating projects internally as well as with printers, agencies or external graphic designers.

OTHER RELEVANT EXPERIENCES AND ACHIEVEMENTS

- Art director and designer of 3D and procedural scenery for flight simulation.
- Prepared, wrote and designed the layout of a presentation on the history of Design (presented at the company Spiria over two days / sessions).
- Freelance Illustrator.
- Painter.
- Script writer of a short and medium length film.
- Actor in two short films.
- Writer and director of a video clip (Stop Motion animation).
- Video editing consultant.
- Actor and scenographer in two College stage plays.
- Composer of soundtracks for student documentary films.
- Designer / co-developer of a video game.

EDUCATION AND DEGREES

1999: BAC in graphic design at the University of Quebec in Montreal. 1995: D.E.C in Arts and Communications at Collège André-Grasset.

CERTIFICATIONS

2015: UX: Mobile evaluation and design at ETS. 2012: Agile / SCRUM at Innobec Technologies.

2010: HTML / CSS integration.

2001: Piano and classical music notation. 1998: Pre-production (script and storyboard).

1989: Drawing / Painting.

AWARDS AND RECOGNITION

2019: *Top of the Year* position for a flight simulator scenery.

2002: The Flightsim Developer's Award for participating in the development of Project Airbus.

2000: Leonard Cohen illustration selected and published in the Saturday Night magazine.

1988: 1st prize in a poster competition for the *Croix Rouge Internationale*.

TECHNOLOGIES (MAC / PC / WINDOWS)

Main Tools: Adobe Creative Suites: XD, Photoshop, Illustrator, Animate, InDesign, Dreamweaver, Premiere Pro etc.

Proto.io, Invision, Balsamiq, Axure, Justinmind et autres outils de prototypage.

Blender, SketchUp, Autodesk GMax / 3DSMax, Poser, Sound Forge, Rebirth, Reason, Samplitude et Audition.

MS Office: Visio, PowerPoint, Excel, Word.

AFFILIATIONS

1998: Co-founder and art director of Lebor Simulations (Development of virtual scenery for flight simulation).